除了我们生活的这个层次  还有其它的
We live on one level of existence, but there are others.
到处充满了隐藏着的其它维度
These hidden dimensions of reality are everywhere.
从许多光年以外
Far away, across the light years.
到我们的脚下
Beneath our feet.
甚至在我们的体内
And even inside you and me.
我们由原子组成
We are made of atoms.
我们眼睛中的原子数量
There are more atoms in your eye,
比已知宇宙中所有星系的星星数量还多
than there are stars and all the galaxies of the known universe
上述情况也适用于任何
The same is true of any solid object
比你的指尖稍大的实体
larger than the tip of your little finger.
我由30万亿亿亿复杂排列的原子组成
I'm a collection of three billion, billion, billion
我是名叫尼尔・德葛拉司・泰森的原子组合体
intricately arranged atoms called Neil Degrasse Tyson.
你们也是一样  只是名字不同
You are a similar collection with a different name.
我们通常不会这么认为
We don't usually think of ourselves this way
因为这个级别的存在超过了我们感官的范畴
because that level of reality lies beyond the realm of our senses.
但是我们不会就此停止
But we're not gonna let that stop us.
我们还要继续探究
We can go deeper into the wonder.
宇宙大探索 第六集
原子使所有事情变得有生气
Atoms let matter do funny things.
要了解水 你需要知道它的原子规律
To understand water, you need to know what its atoms are doing.
每个水分子都是由
Every molecule of water is composed
两个小小的氢原子
of two tiny hydrogen atoms
附着在一个大的氧原子上组成
attached to a larger oxygen atom.
因此我们称之为 一氧化二氢
That's why we call it H20.
如果温度不冷不热
If it's not too hot or too cold,
分子们可以相互翻滚穿行
the molecules can slide and tumble past each other.
分子间还是有一些的粘滞性
There's still some stickiness between the molecules,
但是不足以让它们变的紧密
but not enough to lock them into a rigid solid.
这就是液体的特性
That's what makes something a liquid.
太阳将水加热
The sun warms the water.
给它更多的能量
And with more energy,
分子们移动加快
the molecules move faster.
温度就是这样的
That's all that temperature is.
当分子运到快到足以
Those molecules are moving fast enough
打破彼此间脆弱的联系时
to break the weak bonds that hold them to their neighbors.
就是蒸发
That's evaporation.
我们呼吸的空气
The air we breathe is made of
就是由氮和氧的分子组成
nitrogen and oxygen molecules
再加一些水蒸气和二氧化碳
with a scattering of water vapor and carbon dioxide.
小心
Incoming!
那是冷凝
That's condensation.
露珠就是冷凝战胜蒸发的胜利果实
A dewdrop is the momentary triumph of condensation over evaporation.
这种现象持续下去
And while it lasts,
它就是一个小宇宙 包含它自己的世界
it's a little cosmos with its own worlds...
生物 戏剧性的事情
creatures, drama.
为了探索这滴露珠的广阔领域
To explore the far-flung realms of this dewdrop
我们需要一艘船
we're gonna need a ship.
配上两种引擎
One with twin engines...
科学和想象力
science and imagination.
那是单细胞的草履虫
That's a single-celled paramecium,
它是在露珠中游荡中众多娴熟的猎人之一
one of a multitude of skilled hunter-warriors that roam the dewdrop.
但是它们同时也是猎物
But they, too, are hunted.
长颈虫  草履虫的死敌
The Dileptus. The paramecium's mortal enemy.
草履虫或许可以幸运的直接击杀
The paramecium might get lucky and score a direct hit.
就算不能
Even if it doesn't,
齐射攻击造成的后座力拉开了
the recoil from the barrage will put some distance
草履虫与攻击者之间的距离
between the paramecium and its attacker.
我还能说些什么呢
What can I say?
那就是露珠内的生活
That's life in the dewdrop.
那个小家伙是水熊虫
That little guy is tardigrade,
一种比针尖还小的动物
an animal smaller than the head of a pin.
可别小看它
Don't underestimate them.
水熊虫在这个星球上的历史比我们的还长久
Tardigrades have been living on this planet a lot longer than we have.
他们已存在地球上大约5亿年
About 500 million years.
和我们的数量比例
For every one of us,
至少是1比10亿
there's at least a billion of them.
它们可以在地球上任何地方生存
They can make a living anywhere on earth.
在最高的寒冷的山峰顶端
In the frigid peaks of the tallest mountains,
在喷发的火山口里
in the cauldrons of erupting volcanoes,
在大洋的底部
and in the deep ocean vents at the bottom of the sea.
水熊虫是如此的坚强
Tardigrades are so tough,
它们可以在真空中生存
they can survive naked in the vacuum of space.
它们经历了最近五次的大灭绝
They've survived all five of the most recent mass extinctions on this planet.
如果外星人认为地球是水熊虫的世界
A visitor from another world could be forgiven
那是绝对可以原谅的
for thinking of earth as the planet of the tardigrades.
如果还要看这滴露珠的其它地方 最好继续往前走
If we're ever gonna get to the bottom of this dewdrop better get a move on.
每片叶子和苔藓
Every leaf and tiny clump of moss
都有成千上万的
has hundreds of thousands
显微镜才能看见的嘴巴 称为气孔
of microscopic mouths called Stomata.
植物通过它们呼吸
Plants breathe through them,
吸入二氧化碳
taking in carbon dioxide
呼出我们赖以生存的氧气
and exhaling the oxygen that we need to live.
地球上可以没有我们
The plants can survive without us.
但是我们还有其它动物
But we and all the other animals...
离开它们就死翘翘了
we'd be toast without them.
地球通过阳光获取食物
The plants make food out of sunlight.
我们动物做不到
We animals can't do that.
想看它们是怎么做到的
To see how they do it,
我们还要潜的更深
we have to go deeper,
把我们变小大约1千倍
make ourselves about a thousand times smaller
才能进入它们的宝库
to get into their treasure house,
它们把好东西都藏在里面
the place where they keep the good stuff...
那就是叶绿素
the chlorophyll.
它虽然是个分子 可是却能负责把阳光转换成能量
That's the molecule that converts sunlight into energy.
每个长方形都是一个植物细胞
Every one of those rectangles is a plant cell.
还有那些小绿车 那都是它的能量工厂
And those tiny green vehicles are its energy factories.
如果我们可以窃取它们的商业机密
If we could steal their trade secrets,
又能带来一次崭新的工业革命
it would trigger a new industrial revolution.
但是要偷窥它们
But to spy on them,
我们还得潜得更深
we're gonna need to go deeper still.
想象之舟这次又要将我们带去哪个截然不同的世界呢
What alien world has the ship of the imagination carried us to this time?
它是个宇宙
It's the cosmos...
在露珠里面的宇宙
Contained within a dewdrop.
我们现在做的就是工业间谍活动
We're on an industrial espionage mission.
如果想刺探叶绿体的商业机密
If we can penetrate the trade secrets
叶绿体里的制作过程
of the manufacturing process in that chloroplast,
就当我们的全部未来就靠它了
let's just say our whole future hangs in the balance.
叶绿体利用阳光将水分子
This chloroplast is using sunlight to break water molecules
分解成氢原子和氧原子
into atoms of hydrogen and oxygen.
将氢气与二氧化碳结合产生糖
It combines the hydrogen with carbon dioxide to make sugar,
将氧气作为废气排出
and releases the oxygen as a waste product.
要一探究竟 我们还要潜的更深
To see how it happens, we have to go even deeper,
变得更小
get even smaller.
小到原子级别
We're talking atomic scale.
成功了
Bingo.
这条流水线是分子工业基地的核心
This assembly line is the heartof the molecular industrial complex.
在分子这个级别
At the molecular level,
速度快到我们看不到
things happen too fast for us to see.
所以我们必须让它们慢下来
So we'll have to slow them down
放慢十亿倍
about a billion times.
那些大分子就是二氧化碳
Those larger molecules are carbon dioxide.
每一个分子
Each one of them is made
由1个碳原子和2个氧原子组成
of one carbon and two oxygen atoms.
当阳光照射叶绿素的分子
When sunlight strikes a green molecule of chlorophyll,
就会产生一系列的化学反应
it sets in motion a series of chemical reactions,
分解水分子
breaking apart water molecules
释放活泼的电子
and freeing energetic electrons.
这只是日班的活
And that's just the day shift,
只在日光注入能量时工作
when sunlight supplies the incoming stream of energy.
还有一组不分昼夜的工作
There's a second shift that works day and night
利用预留的太阳能工作
using the solar energy kept in reserve.
自由电子的能量开始工作了
The energy of the free electrons is put to work,
将二氧化碳与水中的氢结合
combining carbon dioxide with hydrogen from the water.
产生糖  用以储存太阳能
The end product is sugar,which stores the solar energy.
叶绿体从事太阳能采集工作
The chloroplast is a three-billion-year-old
长达30亿年
solar energy collector.
微观世界的太阳能电池
This sub-microscopic solar battery
驱动了所有的森林 田地
is what drives all the forests and the fields
甚至是海中的浮游生物
and the plankton of the seas.
还有动物
And the animals.
包括我们
Including us.
太阳能的生物圈
The solar-powered biosphere
比我们整个人类文明收集并处理的能量多出6倍
collects and processes six times more power than our entire civilization
我们了解化学层面的光合作用工作原理
We understand on a chemical level how photosynthesis works.
我们可以在实验室复制这样的过程
We can recreate the process in a laboratory.
但是我们做不到植物这么好
But we're not as good at it as plants are.
这并不奇怪
And it's not surprising,
因为大自然已经这样工作几十亿年了
considering nature has been at this for billions of years,
而我们才刚开始
and we've only just started.
如果我们可以知道
But if we could figure out
光合作用的商业机密
the trade secrets of photosynthesis,
如今我们赖以生存的其它形式的能量
every of other source of energy we depend on today...
煤 石油 天然气都可以淘汰了
coal, oil, natural gas would become obsolete.
光合作用是终极绿色能源
Photosynthesis is the ultimate green power.
它不会污染大气
It doesn't pollute the air
事实上 碳中和人造光合作用可以很大程度上
and is, in fact, carbon neutral. Artificial photosynthesis on a big enough scale
减少温室效应
could reduce the greenhouse effect
所带来的气候变化
that's driving climate change in a dangerous direction.
这里开始蒸发了
Uh-oh, place is evaporating.
该撤了
Time to get out of here.
露珠的生命一闪即逝
How fleeting is the life of a dewdrop.
它在寒冷的夜里从稀薄的空气中凝结而成
It condenses from thin air in the cool of the night,
却在日出之后无影无踪
only to vanish with the heat of the day.
它的居民怎么办 水熊虫呢
And what of its inhabitants, the tardigrades?
它们不会有事的
They'll be fine.
因为它们可以几年不喝水
They can go without water for years.
很难想象
It's hard to imagine,
覆盖地球表面的植物
but plants covered the surface of the earth
几亿年后
for hundreds of millions of years
才开出第一朵花
before they put forth their first flower.
大约1亿年前
That was about a hundred million years ago,
恐龙灭绝前不久
shortly before the dinosaurs were wiped out.
当时世界的颜色一定很单调
Our world must've been a relatively drab-looking place back then,
只有绿色和褐色
dominated by shades of green and brown.
是的那时是有大树和蕨类 还有其它的植物
Yeah, there were giant trees and ferns and other plant life,
但是没有紫色的鸢尾花
but not the purple of an iris
也没有红色的玫瑰花
or the crimson of a red, red rose.
兰花是最早出现的花之一
Orchids were among the first flowering species
现在它们有着最多的品种
to appear on earth, and they're the most diverse.
达尔文特别痴迷马达加斯加的彗星兰
Darwin was particularly fascinated by the comet orchid of Madagascar,
这种花的花粉藏在一条又长又细的花径底部
a flower whose pollen is hidden at the bottom of a very long, thin spur.
预测能力是验证一种理论的最好方法
There can be no stronger test of an idea \than its predictive power.
根据他的物竞天择的进化论基础
On the basis of his theory of evolution through natural selection
达尔文推测
Darwin speculated that somewhere
在马达加斯加岛上 一定有一种会飞的昆虫
on the island of Madagascar, there must live flying insects
长着非常长的舌头
with extraordinarily lengthy tongues,
长的足够接触到那些花粉
ones long enough to reach the pollen.
从没人看过这种动物
No one had ever seen such a beast there,
但是达尔文坚信
but Darwin insisted
肯定有这样的动物存在
that an animal fitting this description must exist.
当时相信他的人不多
Few people at the time believed him.
直到50多年后
It wasn't until more than 50 years later
才证明了达尔文的猜测是正确的
that Darwin was proven right.
1903年 有一种被称为马岛长喙天蛾的蛾子在马达加斯加被发现
In 1903, a huge hawk moth, called the Morgan's sphinx was discovered in Madagascar.
受到彗星兰花粉香味的吸引
Attracted by the Comet Orchid's scent,
这蛾子用它1英尺长的口器吸食花粉
the moth slurps its pollen with its foot-long tongue,
和达尔文猜测的一样
exactly as Darwin expected it would.
更令人惊奇的是 发现这种蛾子时
It's even more amazing that the Morgan's sphinx was discovered
马达加斯加岛上超过90%的雨林已经遭到破坏
when you consider that more than 90% of Madagascar's rain forest had been destroyed.
在达尔文著名的猜测多年后
In the years since Darwin's famous prediction,
这种蛾子很有可能已经灭绝
this moth species could have easily become extinct
就和其它同类一样
with all the others...
它们每一个都是生命诗篇中的独特乐章
every one of them a unique phrase of life's poetry,
由万古的进化写在原子中
written in the atoms by eons of evolution.
丁香花的芬芳
Ah, the fragrance of lilacs.
这种香味
It's one of those scents
让人不禁浮想翩翩
that triggers a whole constellation of associations,
很久前的每个夏天都是如此
all those junes of long ago.
怎会如此
But how does that happen?
味道是怎么会让你的头脑中出现影像的
How does a smell prompt a movie to start running in your head?
那不是我们能看到的
It's not something we can see.
有可能是象光一样的能量波吗
Could it be a wave of energy, like light?
还是一种微观粒子呢
Or is it some kind of microscopic particle?
其实它是一种分子
It's actually a molecule.
每种味道 不论是来自烤焦的面包
Every odor we can sense, whether it comes from burnt toast
还是汽油 或者一片丁香花
gasoline, or a field of lilacs,
都是一大片的分子
is a cloud of molecules.
这些分子有种特定的形状
These molecules have particular shapes.
当我吸入它们时
When I inhale them,
它们刺激我鼻子中一组特定的感受细胞
they stimulate a particular set of receptor cells in my nose.
一种电子信号传递到我的大脑
An electrical signal then travels to my brain,
告诉我这个味道是丁香花的香味
which identifies the scent as lilac.
不同的分子携带不同的味道
Other scents are carried by different molecules
它们的形状也各异
with different shapes.
但当我闻到一朵花 或者篝火
But when I smell a flower or the smoke from a campfire
或者机器的润滑油
or the grease from a motor gear,
通常是涌现出大量的记忆
I'm often flooded with memories.
为什么花香这么简单的东西能够引起强烈的记忆呢
Why is it that a simple thing such as the scent of a flower can trigger powerful memories?
一定和我们的大脑进化方式有关
It has to do with the way our brains have evolved.
当大脑中的嗅神经受到刺激
Our sense of smell kicks in
我们的嗅觉开始工作
when the olfactory nerve in our brain is stimulated.
这种神经就在扁桃体旁边
That nerve is located very close to the amygdala,
是我们情感体验的组成部分
a structure that is integral to our experience of emotion.
也很靠近海马体
It's also very close to the Hippocampus,
产生记忆的地方
which helps us form memories.
神经网络将气味信号
The network of neurons that carry the scent signal
从我的鼻子传递到
from my nose to my brain has been fine-tuned
我这经过上亿年进化的大脑
over hundreds of millions of years of evolution.
这是一种生存机制 给我们发出警告
It's a survival mechanism that can alert us
让我们避开危险
to danger or guide us to safety.
如果你能提前发觉猎食者
If you you can detect the predator
在他发动攻击前
before he's near enough to strike,
或者在被大火困在森林前
or the fire before it traps you in the forest,
就会大大增加你的生存几率
you have a much better chance to survive
然后把你的基因传给下一代
and pass on your genes to the next generation.
花田里的迷人芬芳
That lovely scent from this field of flowers
发出一组独特的神经信号密码
sets off a unique combination of nerve signals.
只有这个密码可以打开我们大脑中
Only that exact combination can crack the safe
储存关于丁香花的记忆保险箱
where the memory of lilacs is stored inside my brain.
啥味道
Wonder who they're for.
我们或许以后会知道
Maybe we'll find out later.
但还有一个隐藏着的宇宙在等着我们
But first, there's another hidden cosmos waiting for us.
植物们静静的呼吸
The plants are softly breathing,
吸入二氧化碳分子
inhaling molecules of carbon dioxide
呼出氧气分子
and exhaling molecules of oxygen.
和我相反
And I'm doing the opposite.
与雪花和指纹不一样
Unlike snowflakes and fingerprints,
同类的原子或分子
atoms or molecules of the same kind
都是完全的相同
are utterly identical to one another.
每次吸气
With every breath we take,
我们吸入的分子数量
we inhale as many molecules as there are stars
和已知宇宙的所有星星数量一样多
in all the galaxies in the visible universe.
呼出的气体与空气流通交换
And every breath we exhale is circulated through the air,
在大地上逐渐混合
and mixed gradually across the continents,
让别人也可以呼吸
it becomes available for others to breathe.
一起呼吸
Breathe with me.
我们大致吸入了1亿的分子
We all just inhaled about 100 million molecules
这些分子曾经被所有的前人
that once passed through the lungs of everyone
呼吸过
who ever lived before us.
想想看 这种原子的再生
Think of it... This kind of atomic reincarnation
将我们与远古的祖先联系在一起
is another link to our distant ancestors,
包括那些最初带领我们探索
including those who first launched us on our explorations
未知宇宙的人
of the unseen universes.
这些宇宙就如同你我一样真实
These universes are as real as you or me,
就在我们的身边
and they surround us.
曾经我们如梦初醒
There was a moment when we awakened
开始用崭新的方法审视和思考
to a new way of thinking and seeing.
那是大约2500年前
It happened about 2,500 years ago
在希腊的小岛上
on the Greek islands that lie
位于东方与西方文明之间
between the empires of the east and west.
商人 游客 水手们自由的融合
There, merchants, tourists and sailors freely mingled,
交流各自关于伟人和神的传说
exchanging tales of great kings and gods.
在爱奥尼亚有个叫米利都的城市 就是今天的土耳其
In Ionian cities and towns like Miletus, in what is now Turkey,
一些现代生活的最基本元素
the most fundamental elements
在那里出现了
of the way we live now first appeared.
第一次对生活形式的重现
Here, for the first time, reenactments of aspects of life
由专业人士创作并演绎
created and executed by professionals
期待可以深深感动观众的内心
with the expectation of touching something deep within the hearts of the audience,
或者只是逗他们开心
or just making them laugh...
诞生了第一场演出 戏剧还有喜剧
The first plays, dramas and comedies, were performed.
还有一种极其崭新的概念
Here, also, was born a radical new idea:
民治政府
Government by the people.
从最初模糊的不完美的概念 到如今的民主
The first inklings, imperfect then as now, of a democracy,
普通民众也可以拥有某些权力的观念
and the notion that the ordinary citizen might possess certain rights
在那时 在这里诞生萌芽
come to us from this time and place.
但在我看来 这个古代世界带给我们的
But in my view, the most revolutionary innovation of all
最革命性的创新观念是
to come to us from this ancient world was the idea
自然事件并不是众神给我们的惩罚或奖励
that natural events were neither punishment nor reward from capricious gods.
大自然的规律不一定要用
The workings of nature could be explained
超自然力量来解释
without invoking the supernatural.
表达出这种观念的第一人
The first person to express this thought
名叫 泰利斯
was a man named Thales.
希腊哲学家
当闪电或地震时
When the thunder clapped or the earth quaked,
并不是因为我们的所作所为触怒了严厉的众神
it was not because something you did had somehow displeased the very demanding gods.
只是一种我们可以理解的自然过程的结果
No, it was the result of natural processes that we were capable of understanding.
尽管没有任何记录他原话的书籍留存下来
Though none of the books he is said to have written survive,
泰利斯的思想光芒依然照耀我们
Thales kindled a flame that still burns to this day:
宇宙运行的井井有条的原因
The very idea of cosmos out of chaos,
宇宙由我们可以理解的自然法则控制的这种观念
a universe governed by the order of natural laws that we can actually figure out.
这种伟大的观念在泰利斯的头脑中萌芽
This is the epic adventure that began in the mind of Thales.
仅仅在泰利斯身后100年
Only a century following Thales' death,
又一个天才出现了
another genius came along.
他与众不同的是
And he, more than any other,
第一个发现了
was the first to discover the existence
我们周围未知宇宙的存在
of the hidden universes that surround us.
来自阿夫季拉的德谟克利特是为真正的科学家
Democritus of Abdera was a true scientist,
充满探索宇宙激情的男人
a man with a passionate desire to know the cosmos
也很会享受
and to have fun.
他曾说 "没有狂欢的生活
This is the man who once said, "a life without parties
...就像没有尽头的漫漫长路"
would be like an endless road without an end."
这就样吗
You mean, that's it?
就这么简单吗
That's all there is?
只是虚无中的一堆原子
Just a bunch of atoms in a void?
然也
Yep.
你想想看
Well, think about it.
这个世界必然是
The world has to be made
由虚无中无数的不可见的微粒组成
of countless indivisible particles in a void.
否则万物就不会移动 生长 被分离或改变
Otherwise, nothing could move or grow, be divided or changed.
如果没有原子和容纳它们的空旷太空的话
Without atoms and empty space for them to move in,
这个世界会变得像铁板一块 死气沉沉
the world would be solid, static and dead.
别伤心了 少年
so don't be sad, my friends.
想想那无尽的可能性吧
Just think of the infinite possibilities
由那些原子排列组合所带来的可能性
that arise from different arrangements of those atoms.
向这杯的酒 还有酒中的原子们致敬
Here's to the atoms in this cup and in this wine...
还有它们带来的欢乐
And to the laughter they make possible.
当时的酒杯都由泥土烧制而成
遍布酒杯的泥土
Dispersed through the Clay of the cup
都是用显微镜才能看到的矿物微粒
are microscopic mineral grains,
晶体的一种
different kinds of crystals,
每个都有与众不同的原子结构
each with its own distinctive atomic architecture.
矿物结构很精妙
Mineral structures are exquisite,
但是它们的结构形式有限
but they have a limited repertoire.
一粒石英就是一个由3个相同原子组成的晶格集合体
A grain of quartz is a lattice of the same three atoms
没有变化 不断重复
repeated, without variation, over and over again.
即使是相对复杂的矿物晶格 比如黄宝石
Even a relatively complex mineral lattice like topaz,
由10个左右的原子组成
composed of ten or so atoms,
也只是相同的原子结构
can only repeat the identical atomic structure
不断重复
again and again.
为了转换到另一个维度
为了将它从不断重复的晶格束缚中释放
to free it from the lattice prison of endless repetition,
你需要一个可以从任何方向与其它原子相结合的原子
you need an atom that can bond in all directions with other atoms like itself
它也要能与其它不同的原子相结合
as well as with atoms of different kinds.
看 碳原子
Behold the carbon atom...
地球上生命不可缺少的元素
the essential element for life on earth.
为什么
Why?
碳之所以特殊 是因为它可以一次与最多4种原子结合
Carbon is special because it can bond with up to four other atoms at a time.
它可以与许多其它种类的原子结合
It can connect with many different kinds of atoms,
也包括其它碳原子
as well as other carbon atoms.
它可以弯曲成环状
It can curl into rings
也可以连成一条线
and string together into chains,
组成远比任何一种晶体都复杂的分子
building molecules far more complex than any crystal.
其它原子都没有这种灵活性
No other atom has the same flexibility.
就算拥有类似化学属性的原子也不行
Even atoms that have similar chemical properties,
比如 硅
like silicon,
也无法像碳这样组成丰富多样的分子
can't form the amazing variety of molecules built on carbon.
这种碳基分子 我们称为 蛋白质
The carbon-based molecules we call proteins,
组成生命的分子
the molecules of life,
包含了成千上万的原子
contain literally hundreds of thousands of atoms.
碳原子是世界上一切生物分子的支柱
Carbon atoms are the backbone of the molecules that make every living thing on earth,
包括我们
including us.
这就是岩石和生物的区别
That's the difference between rocks and living things.
生命可以制造出大量的
Life can make enormous molecules
有着惊人体积和复杂性的分子
of stunning size and complexity,
自由自在地随机应变
freeing matter to improvise,
进化
evolve,
甚至 爱
and even love.
孩子的父亲 您别担心
Take it easy, dad.
他并没有真的碰到的她
He never actually touched her.
日常生活中以原子这个层面上来说
In everyday life on our world, on the scale of atoms,
物体绝对不会相互接触到对方
material objects never really touch.
每个原子的中心都有一个原子核
Each atom has a tiny nucleus at its center,
被力线电子云所包围
surrounded by an electron cloud of lines of force.
当原子彼此接近时
As the atoms approach each other,
男孩的电子云
the boy's electron clouds
推开女孩的电子云
push away the girl's.
超过99.9%的原子物质都集中在它的原子核中
More than 99.9% of the matter of any atom is concentrated in its nucleus.
原子核被电子云包围
The nucleus is surrounded by an electron cloud
电子云形成无形的力场
which produces an invisible field of force,
就像减震器
and acts like a shock absorber.
电子云的结构决定了元素的本质
The configuration of the electron cloud determines the nature of an element.
以地球上物质的正常情况来说
In the ordinary course of things here on earth,
原子核永远不会彼此接触
the nuclei never touch.
我们有接触的感觉
We have a sensation of touching,
那只不过是看不见的力场
but that's really just our invisible force fields
相互重迭的同时相互排斥
overlapping and repelling each other.
相较于原子的其它部分 原子核非常小
The nucleus is very small compared to the rest of the atom.
如果原子像这个教堂这么大
If an atom were the size of this cathedral,
原子核的尺寸也就是那粒灰尘的大小
its nucleus would be the size of that mote of dust.
原子的大部分是空旷的空间
An atom is mostly empty space.
为了理解事物的本质
To understand the nature of matter,
我们要去更深的地方
we have to go deeper still,
去一个比原子还小10万倍的地方
to a place 100,000 times smaller than the atom:
那就是它的原子核
Its nucleus.
宇宙中最简单 但又最丰富的原子是氢原子
The simplest and most plentiful atom in the cosmos is hydrogen.
它的原子核只有一个质子
Its nucleus is a single proton,
所以它在元素周期表中位于第一位
which makes hydrogen element number one.
围绕着它的云
The clouds that surround it
是它唯一的电子可以运行的范围
are the realms where the atom's lone electron is permitted to roam.
原子核有两个质子时会是什么情况
What happens when you have a nucleus with two protons?
质子相互排斥
Protons repel each other.
为了让它们保持在原子核内
In order to hold them together in a nucleus,
你还需要另一种粒子 称之 中子
you need other particles called neutrons.
它们的工作是防止质子出轨
Their job is to keep the protons from getting out of line.
它们用强大的核引力压制质子
They overwhelm the protons
原子核有2个质子的元素排名第2
A nucleus with two protons is element number two,
名曰 氦
otherwise known as helium.
原子核有6个质子的元素排名第6
A nucleus with six protons is element number six,
就是碳
which is carbon,
生命的基石
the fundamental building block of life.
金元素的原子核有79个质子
The nucleus of a gold atom has 79 protons.
在周围的云中 它们吸引了79个电子
They attract 79 electrons in clouds around it
光与这些电子的互动
The way light interacts with those electrons
就是黄金闪光的原因
is what makes gold glitter.
原子核中每增加一个质子
Every additional proton in the nucleus
都需要有足够的中子把它们聚集在一起
requires enough neutrons to bind them together...
在一定程度上
Up to a point.
你能塞进原子核的中子数量是有上限的
There's an upper limit to the number of neutrons you can stuff into a nucleus
否则会变得不稳定
before it becomes unstable.
有个地方
I know a place
不同原子的原子核
where the nuclei of different atoms
能够相互接触
actually do touch each other.
太阳看上去像个实体
The sun looks like a solid object,
但并不是这样的
but it's not.
它把所有的原子都加热到了气态
It's so hot that all its atoms are always in their gaseous state.
地球上将原子束缚产生液态和固体的粘合力
The bonds that join atoms to make solids and liquids on earth
不足以承受炽热太阳的热量
are not strong enough to withstand the heat of the broiling sun
那些耀眼气体的弧形气流使地球看上去渺小
Those arcing streams of incandescent gas that dwarf the earth
其实它们都受到太阳表面之下发射出来的力场的磁力线引导
are guided by magnetic lines of force that emanate from below the surface of the sun.
太阳怎么会这么热
Why is the sun so hot?
因为它惊人的引力
Because its own stupendous gravity
将原子们积压在一起
is squeezing its atoms together.
引力的能量转换成
The energy of gravity is being transformed
移动原子的能量
into the energy of moving atoms.
那就是热的来源
That's what heat is.
越到太阳的内部
The deeper we go into the sun,
挤压的力量越大
the greater the squeezing
温度也越高
and the higher the temperature.
在太阳的中心
In the heart of the sun,
原子的移动速度快到 它们碰撞时发生融化 原子核发生接触
the atoms are moving so fast that when they collide, they fuse. Their nuclei touch.
太阳就是核聚变反应堆
The sun is a nuclear fusion reactor,
由它的引力来维系
held together by its own gravity.
它在向内拉的引力和向外推的热浪间取得平衡
It's balanced between the inward pull of gravity and the outward push of its hot gases.
这种平衡持续几十亿年
That balance has lasted billions of years,
提供了使地球上生物进化成为可能的稳定性
providing stability that made possible the evolution of life on earth.
在太阳的核心 氢融合后变成氦
In the sun's core, the fusion of hydrogen into helium
以光子的形式释放核能
releases nuclear energy in the form of photons.
这些光的微粒
These particles of light
慢慢的来到表面
slowly work their way to the surface,
就是我们所见的日光
where they're seen as sunlight.
氦原子就是太阳核反应的残渣
Helium is the ash of the sun's nuclear furnace.
太阳是一颗中等尺寸的恒星
The sun is a medium-sized star.
它的核心温度只不过1千万度
Its core is only a lukewarm ten million degrees...
只够融化氢原子
hot enough to fuse hydrogen,
却不足以融化氦原子
but too cold to fuse helium.
银河系中有很多恒星
There are many stars in the galaxy
比太阳热得多
that get much hotter,
因为它们质量更大
because they're more massive
引力更大
and have more gravity.
这些恒星将氦融化成更重的元素 比如 碳和氧
Such stars fuse helium into heavier elements, like carbon and oxygen.
等它们老了
In their old age,
它们慢慢的将这些元素散播到太空中
they gently diffuse these elements into space.
还有些恒星 质量更大
Other stars, more massive yet,
一生苦短 英年早逝
live fast and die young
卒于灾难性的超新星大爆炸
in cataclysmic supernova explosions.
我们的银河系中 每一百年 这样的恒星就会变成超新星
In our galaxy, such stars go supernova about once a century.
这些爆炸比太阳核心热的多得多
Those explosions are far hotter than the core of the sun
热的足够把铁元素变成更重的元素
hot enough to transform elements like iron into all the heavier ones
并把它们喷向太空
and spew them into space.
大麦哲伦星云
The large magellanic cloud
使我们银河系的邻居
is a neighboring galaxy of our milky way.
可以在南半球的星空中看到
It's visible in the skies of the Southern hemisphere.
当超新星爆炸时
When a supernova explodes,
它的亮度超过它的整个星系
its brightness rivals that of its entire galaxy.
但这些光也只是爆炸产生的能量中的大约1%
But all that light is only about one percent of the energy liberated in the explosion.
其它的能量化成宇宙中最常见
The rest of the energy is carried off by the most common
也最神秘的微粒
and the most mysterious particles in the cosmos.
现在就有几万亿的这种微粒穿过你的身体
There are trillions of them passing through you right now,
然而即使为了找到一个这样的微粒
and yet tracking down even one of them
也需要我们去到地球上最离奇的地方
will take us to one of the strangest places on earth.
追踪野生的中微子
Stalking the wild neutrino
是最小众的运动
is the rarest of sport.
追踪它们的难度 难得令人惊讶
The lengths one must go to track them down is nothing short of astonishing
欢迎来到超级神冈探测器
Welcome to Super Kamiokande,
日本地下中微子探测器的内部
the subterranean Japanese neutrino detection chamber.
我们身处地表之下超过半英里
We're more than a half mile beneath earth's surface.
也就是大约1公里
你或许会问 哪个正常人
You might ask, "well, who in their right mind
会把天文台埋在这么深的地下
would bury an astronomical observatory so far underground?"
这些人狩猎宇宙中最神出鬼没的猎物
Those who hunt the most elusive prey in the cosmos:
中微子
The neutrino.
这个庞大的光探测器数组
This enormous array of light detectors
围绕着5万吨蒸馏水
surrounding 50,000 tons of distilled water
设计这个陷阱只为了抓捕中微子
is a trap designed to catch neutrinos only.
其它粒子 例如宇宙射线
Other particles, such as cosmic rays...
大部分是从太空中落下的质子和电子
mostly protons and electrons that rain down from space...
无法穿过我们头顶的岩石
cannot get through all that rock above us.
但这些对中微子来说都不是障碍
But matter poses no obstacle to a neutrino.
中微子可以穿过100光年厚的铁板
A neutrino could pass through 100 light-years of steel
甚至不会减速
without even slowing down.
中微子几乎不受其它物质影响
Neutrinos hardly interact with matter at all
这就是为什么我们需要如此大费周章
That's why you need so much of it to catch even one of them.
在很罕见的情况下
On those rare occasions when a neutrino
中微子和其它微粒发生冲突
actually does collide with a particle of ordinary matter,
它会产生一个幽灵般的环形闪光
it produces a ghostly, ring-shaped flash of light.
我们守株待兔
We're lying in wait
等一个几乎没有重量的微粒
for a particle that weighs next to nothing.
甚至比电子
Even the miniscule electron
还轻100万倍
has more than a million times its mass...
那里
There!
1987年 当大麦哲伦星云的超新星爆炸时
When the supernova in the large magellanic cloud blew its top in 1987
这就是当时这里出现的景象
this is what it would have looked like in here.
请记住 大麦哲伦星云
Now remember, the large magellanic cloud
在我们的南半球
is in our Southern hemisphere,
所以这些中微子不是穿过
so the neutrinos didn't come through
我们头顶上半英里的岩石
that half-mile of rock above us,
而是必须穿过我们身下
they had to pass through the thousands of miles
几千英里的岩石和铁才能到达这里
of rock and iron below us to reach this detector.
但是最酷的事情是
But the coolest thing was that those neutrinos
中微子比超新星发出的光早3小时到达地球
hit earth three hours before the light from the supernova did.
如果没有什么能比光跑得快
If nothing can travel faster than light,
这又是怎么回事呢
how could that possibly be?
星之将死
This is a dead star walking.
看上去好像挺正常 但是在它的深处大灾难已经发生
It may look normal, but deep within it something cataclysmic is happening
这颗蓝色的超级巨大的恒星
This blue super giant star
内部即将发生爆炸
has already begun to explode inside.
如同即将沉船上的老鼠 慌不择路
Like rats deserting a sinking ship, the neutrinos
即将爆炸的恒星内部产生的中微子
produced in the heart of the exploding star
以接近光速的速度向外逃逸
race outward at near the speed of light,
几秒内穿过覆盖物
through overlying mass in only a few seconds
但是爆炸气体的冲击波
But the shock wave of the exploding gas
从恒星内部缓缓踱出
plods along from the center of the star
只有光速的万分之一
at 1/10,000 the speed of light
直到最后抵达
until it finally reaches
恒星的表面
the star's surface,
变成了1987年的超新星
turning it into supernova 1987a.
要好几个小时
It took hours for the explosion
爆炸才能到达表面 然后向外喷发
to reach the surface of the star and blow it wide open,
将极度炙热的内核炸开
exposing the super hot core.
中微子已经赢在了起跑在线
The neutrinos had an insurmountable head start.
这就是为什么闪光会比中微子晚这么多到达地球
That's why the flash of light arrived on earth so much later than the shower of neutrinos.
在「野生」中微子被捕获前
Before anyone had ever snared the wild neutrino,
它已经存在于理论物理学家的脑海中
it existed in the mind of a theoretical physicist.
就如同查尔斯・达尔文知道
Just as Charles Darwin knew
必定有一种超级长鼻生物生活在马达加斯加
there must be an extremely long-nosed creature flying around somewhere in Madagascar
一位名叫沃尔夫冈・泡利的20世纪物理学家
a 20th-century physicist named Wolfgang Pauli...
致力于寻找一种微粒
was desperately seeking a particle
用来拯救现代物理学的支柱之一
to rescue one of the pillars of modern physics,
能量守恒定律
the law of the conservation of energy.
我为什么没有退缩
So why didn't I flinch?
因为科学定律与其它人类活动的根本区别
Because the laws of science differ fundamentally from those of other human endeavors
要将一种设想变成科学定律
In order for an idea to become a scientific law,
必须要无懈可击
it has to unbreakable.
这就是为何我愿意赌上我的脸
That's why I was willing to bet this face
来证明能量守恒定律
on the laws of conservation of energy.
如果你在家自己尝试
Now, if you try this at home,
千万小心不要推这个球
take care not to give the cannonball a push.
那会增加能量
That's adding energy,
这球肯定会回来造成伤害
and the ball will surely come back and do some damage.
只要像这样轻轻放手
You just have to let it go, like this.
抬起这个球
By lifting the ball,
你给它势能
you give it gravitational energy,
使它可能坠落并且加速
which is the potential to fall and accelerate.
球在弧度底部时速度达到最大
The cannonball is going fastest when it's at the bottom of its arc
在那个时候
and at that moment,
它把所有的势能转化成动能
it's converted all of its gravitational energy to the energy of motion.
摇摆时 球不断转换能量
As it swings, the cannonball is constantly exchanging
从一种转换到另一种
one of these two kinds of energy for the other,
但是能量的总量保持不变
but the total amount of energy remains constant.
这就是能量守恒定律的例子
That's an example of the law of conservation of energy.
放开球的那刻
Once the cannonball is released,
它就无法获得更多的能量
it can never gain more energy than it had to begin with.
它不可能飞过来打到我的鼻子
It has no way to fly up and break my nose.
能量这笔账永远是平衡的
The energy accounting books are always strictly balanced.
做不得假
There's no such thing as cheating.
在20世纪
So in the 20th century,
当科学家首次精确测量出原子的能量
when physicists first calculated the energy of atoms precisely,
他们惊讶的发现了
they were startled to discover
违背这个定律的情况
an apparent violation of this law.
他们发现在一些放射性原子中
They found that in some radioactive atoms,
原子核自发的喷出一个电子
the nucleus can spontaneously eject an electron.
将原子转变成另一种元素
This transforms the atom into a different element.
物理学家迷惑了
The physicists were mystified.
逃逸电子的能量
The energy of the escaped electron
加上新元素的能量
plus that of the new element
少于原有原子核的能量
adds up to less than the energy in the original nucleus.
定律指出
But the law says,
能量既不会凭空产生 也不会凭空消失
"thou shall not destroy or create energy."
那么那些能量去了哪里
So where did the missing energy go?
1930年
In 1930...
沃尔夫冈・泡利预测
Wolfgang Pauli predicted
一定有一种未知的微粒
there must be an undiscovered particle,
带走了这些能量
one that makes off with the missing energy.
当时 沃尔夫冈・泡利感叹
At the time, Pauli lamented
如此微小的虚幻微粒
that such a phantom particle might be so minute,
迅速而难以琢磨
swift and evasive
可能永远都探测不到了
as to forever defy detection.
好在那只是他罕有的一次错误预测
But that was a rare failure of his imagination
因为科学家总是不断
because science is always searching
寻找探索的新方法
for a way to go deeper still.
几十年后
A generation later,
在核反应堆的辐射中
Pauli's neutrinos were actually detected for the first time
中微子第一次被人们探测到
in radiation from a nuclear reactor.
虽然很艰难 但从那之后我们不断找到更多的
And we've been finding them, with difficulty, ever since.
如今 有些科学家们
There are scientists today
尝试利用那些中微子
who are trying to find a way to ride those neutrinos
来研究时间的起源
all the way back to the beginning of time.
一起去看看他们的成就  那是一面永恒之墙
We'll go as far as they have gone to come up against the wall of forever.
永恒之墙并不新鲜
The wall of forever is nothing new.
我们的祖先也遇到过
Our ancestors came up against it
几乎就在他们第一次开始想象时
almost as soon as they first started imagining it.
几千年前 公元前13世纪
A million dawns ago, in the 13th century bc,
埃及人建造了阿布辛贝勒神庙
the Egyptian built this temple at Abu Simbel
纪念法老王拉美西斯二世
to honor the Pharaoh Ramses II,
在这里留下了四座巨大的石像
depicted here in four colossal statues.
在这位伟大君主之上真正的王者其实是鹰首太阳神
Reigning even above even this mighty king is the falcon-headed Ra-Harakhti
太阳之神
God of the sun.
这座神庙被设计成每年只有两次
The temple was designed so that the light from the rising sun
旭日的霞光金辉才会射入神殿
could only enter the sanctuary on two days every year.
当光线照进神庙
As the rays enter the temple,
在贯穿整个神殿前
they burnish the statues of the gods with their golden light
日光使众神的石像闪耀着金色的光芒
before penetrating the sanctuary.
但是 仍有一位神的石像依然处在阴影中
Even then, one God remains in shadow.
普塔 创造之神
Ptah, lord of creation,
彷佛暗示宇宙的起源注定永远神秘
as if the origin of the universe must forever be concealed.
感受阳光照在脸上
Feel the sun on your face.
使你温暖的能量
The energy that warms you
来自几千万年前
began its journey some ten million years ago
太阳的核心
in the heart of the sun.
与中微子不同
Unlike neutrinos,
质子需要
the photons needed
这么久的时间才能从核心到达表面
that long to work their way out from the core to the surface.
为什么
Why?
因为它们与太阳的原子每秒发生几十亿次的碰撞
Because they were colliding billions of times per second with the sun's atoms
每次撞击都将它们推向不同的方向
every collision sending them off in a random direction.
它们一旦到达表面
But once they finally reached the surface,
它们就彻底解放 以光的速度
they were free to dash nonstop, at the speed of light
只用区区8分20秒 就来到你的面前
in a mere eight minutes and 20 seconds from the sun to you
一千万岁高龄的阳光
Ten-million-year-old light on your face.
当那光离开太阳核心时 又是怎么的景象呢
What was happening when that light left the heart of the sun?
宇宙年历将宇宙
The cosmic calendar compresses
整整138亿年的历史
the entire 13.8 billion year history
压缩到一年的时间内
of the universe into a single year.
每个月代表10亿年
Every month represents about a billion years.
一天就是4千万年
Every day, about 40 million years.
宇宙的历史如此悠久 在年历上
The universe is so old that, on the cosmic calendar,
1千万年前 也只不过是
ten million years ago only takes us back as far as...
这一年的最后一天的下午6点
6:00 P.M. on the last evening of the last day of the year
那我们呢
And what about us?
人类还没开始进化
Humans had yet to evolve.
1千万年前
Ten million years ago,
我们的祖先还是类人猿
our ancestors were anthropoid apes,
活跃在非洲的丛林中
swinging through the trees of Africa.
对我们来说 1千万年好像很久远
To us, ten million years seems like a long time,
但是对于宇宙来说
but it's only the length of an afternoon
那只不过是半天而已
on the timescale of the cosmos.
45亿年前 太阳开始放出光芒
The sun began fusing hydrogen 4,500 million years ago...
宇宙历上的8月31号
August 31 on the cosmic calendar.
我们的银河系
Our milky way galaxy
大约100亿岁
is about 10,000 million years old.
第一个星系比它还早几十亿年
The first galaxies formed about a few billion years earlier.
有东西阻挡我们回到更远的过去
Something keeps me from going any further back in time.
是什么呢
What is this?
是光与时间的本质
It's the nature of light and time.
因为光的速度有限
Because light travels at a finite speed,
我们所看到的宇宙 其实只是过去的光
to look across space is to look back in time.
看得越远
So the farther we see,
看到的光越古老
the older the light.
这是我们所能看到宇宙历史上最古老的光
This is as far back in the history of the cosmos as we can see with light.
这是宇宙刚诞生的样子
It's a baby picture of universe,
只有38万岁
when it was only 380,000 years old.
宇宙历上最初的15分钟
That's 15 minutes into January 1 on the cosmic calendar
我们用微波望远镜看向宇宙的尽头
If we look as far as we can see in any direction using microwave telescopes
看到的就是这样
this is what we see,
大爆炸留下的光晕
the glow left over from the Big Bang.
想象一下 可观测宇宙的所有物质和能量
Imagine that all the matter and energy of the observable universe
都被浓缩成这样的大小
was concentrated into something no larger than this
这就是当时宇宙的大小
That's the size of the universe
当它只有一分之一万亿岁时
when it was a trillionth of a trillionth of a trillionth of a second old
几千亿个星系的物质与能量
All the matter and energy of the hundred billion galaxies
如今扩展到方圆几十亿光年的范围
now splayed out across the billions of light-years
曾经都被禁锢在这个弹珠大小的东西内
were once pent up in something the size of a marble
你能想象出那颗弹珠有多紧密吗
Can you imagine how tightly packed that marble must have been?
稠密得使任何光都无法穿过
Far too dense for any kind of light to move through it,
但这阻碍不了中微子
but no obstacle for the likes of neutrinos.
大爆炸必定产生了数量惊人的中微子
The big bang must have produced stupendous numbers of neutrinos,
它们顺畅地穿过那些紧密得难以置信的物质
which flew unhindered through that inconceivable crush of matter
使它们几乎无法被探测的最关键因素是
The very thing that makes them almost impossible to detect
它们可以穿过遮掩时间起源的厚重幕布
is what allows neutrinos to sail through the curtain that conceals the beginning of time
它们在哪里
Where are they now?
在这里 在那里
They are here, they're there,
宇宙中无处不在
everywhere throughout the universe.
宇宙诞生时中微子就在你的内心深处
Neutrinos from creation are within you.
从一个弹珠
From a marble...
到整个宇宙
To the cosmos.
这是一条泰利斯和德谟克利特2500年前带我们走上的路
This is the road that Thales and Democritus put us on some 2,500 years ago...
无尽的探索之路
a road of endless searching,
不断的有条不紊的探索新的世界
a relentless, systematic hunt for new worlds
并且不断加深对自然的理解
and an ever-deepening understanding of nature.
你们中有人会接过火炬 带领我们走上一条更宽广的大路吗
Who among you will pick up that torch and take us down that next stretch of road?